Register of the Firing Line (Television Program) broadcast records 80040.4089238
Hoover Institution Archives
- Episode Guide, 1966-1999
  - "The Death Penalty: Part I" Guests: Koch, Ed, 1924-: Boleyn, Susan.: Berns, Walter, 1919-: Glasser, Ira.: Botstein, Leon.: Bright, Stephen B., 1948-: Stevenson, Bryan., 24 May 1994 (Item Program Number S1014, 2404)
    Program details: This pair of shows reaches the shouting stage more than once. But as much as this topic has been discussed over the years, we do learn some new things about it, as well as about the perspectives of people who specialize in it. EK: "Why do you think that the Lindbergh law is so effective? After the Lindbergh federal law--which said that if you kidnapped someone and they were not returned alive, you were subject to the death penalty, whereas if they were returned alive, you might be subject to life imprisonment--kidnappings overwhelmingly across this country ended. There were very few, whereas there were enormous numbers before that law...." IG: "Well, that may have something to do with the fact that the nature of homicides is very different. Kidnapping is a calculated crime; homicide is not, as you well know." ... LB: "Ultimately, age and longevity give people an opportunity for redemption.... The reason to not kill someone--life imprisonment--is, even though they never get out, there is some possibility in life for redemption."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1277
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7211
  - "The Death Penalty: Part II" Guests: Koch, Ed, 1924-: Boleyn, Susan.: Glasser, Ira.: Botstein, Leon.: Bright, Stephen B., 1948-, 24 May 1994 (Item Program Number S1015, 2405)
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1278
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7212
  - "Where Is the GOP Going? Part I: Health Care" Guests: Rusher, William A., 1923-: Keyes, Alan L. (Alan Lee), 1950-: Noonan, Peggy, 1950-: Frum, David, 1960-: Brookhiser, Richard.: Rollins, Ed., 8 August 1994 (Item Program Number S1016, 2406)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 137: 22
    Transcript: Box/Folder 186: 9
    Program details: It was two months before congressional Democrats would drop the Clinton-inspired effort at a comprehensive reordering of America's health care, and three months before the stunning Gingrich/Contract with America Republican election victory, and "this seminar by conservative Republicans," as Mr. Buckley describes it, ranges from first principles to the latest legislative battle. RB: "I live in New York City. I live in the headquarters of liberalism. I think the Clinton bill should be named the New York City Liberal Democratic Doctor's Conversion Act." ... AK: "There is only one issue on the table, only one issue that I think goes to everything in our politics, and that issue is the erosion and moral collapse of this country. The moral character of this people is in some areas dead, in other areas dying, and if we don't recover it, the whole system, economically and politically, will collapse." ... WAR: "This may be heresy in a group as conservative as this ... I think we'd better give up the idea that we're going to shrink government back to something that would have looked good in 1890. Gang, we are not going to shrink government. There are a quarter of a billion people in the United States of America; they have a lot of different wishes and desires and impulses and needs. And government is going to be in the picture more than you or I would want it to be." ... ER: "Republicans want to do everything the Democrats do for 80 per cent of the cost, and that's a system that will not work."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1279
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7213
  - "Where Is the GOP Going? Part II: Abortion" Guests: Rusher, William A., 1923-: Keyes, Alan L. (Alan Lee), 1950-: Noonan, Peggy, 1950-: Frum, David, 1960-: Brookhiser, Richard.: Rollins, Ed., 8 August 1994 (Item Program Number S1017, 2407)
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1280
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7214
  - "Where Is the GOP Going? Part III: Big Government" Guests: Rusher, William A., 1923-: Keyes, Alan L. (Alan Lee), 1950-: Noonan, Peggy, 1950-: Frum, David, 1960-: Brookhiser, Richard.: Rollins, Ed., 8 August 1994 (Item Program Number S1018, 2408)
    Transcript: Box/Folder 186: 10
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1281
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7215
  - "Where Is the GOP Going? Part IV: Questions and Answers from Young Republicans" Guests: Rusher, William A., 1923-: Keyes, Alan L. (Alan Lee), 1950-: Noonan, Peggy, 1950-: Frum, David, 1960-: Brookhiser, Richard.: Rollins, Ed., 8 August 1994 (Item Program Number S1019, 2409)
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1282
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7216
  - "Separation of Church and State: Part I: The Constitutional Aspect" Guests: Graglia, Lino A.: Neuhaus, Richard John.: Paulsen, Michael.: Dershowitz, Alan M.: Lynn, Barry W.: Dorsen, Norman.: Teitel, Ruti G.: Kinsley, Michael E., 8 September 1994 (Item Program Number S1020, 2410)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 138: 1
    Transcript: Box/Folder 186: 11
    Program details: A kaleidoscopic pair of shows, as rapid-fire duels alternate with calm--and deeply informative--reflection. ND: "With respect to the church-state issue ... there are two provisions in the First Amendment, and they look in opposite directions ..." WFB: "I think it's complementary. Don't you agree, Father Neuhaus? My chances of practicing my religion increase to the extent that yours decrease of establishing a religion." RJN: "Your point is exactly right, and of course that drives to the heart of an important disagreement. The two provisions of the one religion clause are not, in my judgment, to be balanced one against the other.... The clear purpose of the religion clause ... --and it is grammatically one clause and in purpose one clause--is to protect religious freedom." ... AD: "If Abraham today had gone out to sacrifice Isaac, I would indict him for attempted murder." LG: "Would you defend him?" AD: "I would defend him." ... WFB: "If I say I believe in incest?" AD: "I would like to try to talk you out of it." WFB: "There're a lot of interesting ways of handling that question, but one that immediately catches my attention is that it's proscribed by the Bible." AD: "And so how do you persuade somebody who doesn't believe in the Bible?" WFB: "The Bible I consider to be the centerpiece from which the moral culture of our society springs." ND: "The Athenians had a highly developed theoretical construct that guided the people. There are other ways of developing values."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1285
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7219
  - "Separation of Church and State: Part II: The Social Aspect" Guests: Graglia, Lino A.: Neuhaus, Richard John.: Paulsen, Michael.: Dershowitz, Alan M.: Lynn, Barry W.: Dorsen, Norman.: Teitel, Ruti G.: Kinsley, Michael E., 8 September 1994 (Item Program Number S1021, 2411)
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1284
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7218
  - "Perspectives on Health Care: Part I: Managed Care" Guests: Campbell, Carroll.: Burton, Marion.: Middleton, Francis.: Scott, Richard.: Seward, John.: Timmerman, William., 15 September 1994 (Item Program Number S1022, 2412)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 138: 2
    Transcript: Box/Folder 186: 12
    Program details: These shows were taped 11 days before Senate Majority Leader George Mitchell withdrew the Clinton health-care proposal from Senate consideration. But as we know in retrospect, the issue by no means died with the bill. These shows help us to understand why the Clinton bill died, and to evaluate what has happened since. Dr. Seward: "If your basic premise is that my only purpose is to cut costs,... this is the area that I think we have to look at very very closely.... For instance,... just do generic prescribing, period. I'm sorry, from a clinical standpoint as a practicing family physician, there are certain trade name drugs that I think from a true chemical standpoint are the only things to provide.... Whenever you talk about costs, somehow you have to get it back to, How is it going to affect that patient?" ... Gov. Campbell: "There is a school of thought that exists in Washington that comes down from on high from some of the professors at Harvard--with whom I had the privilege to sit for countless hours and listen and learn very little--that they know best what we should do, that they understand more than we do." ... Mr. Scott: "As we know, the government cannot run health care. The average Medicaid recipient gets more than twice as much health care as the average employed person in this country. And they don't like the care, the doctors don't like how they're getting paid, nor does the hospital, and there's no control on quality."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1286
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7220
  - "Perspectives on Health Care: Part II: The Elderly" Guests: Campbell, Carroll.: Burton, Marion.: Boger, Jack.: Keenan, Joseph.: Seward, John.: McCurdy, Layton., 15 September 1994 (Item Program Number S1023, 2413)
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1287
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7221
  - "Perspectives on Health Care: Part III: Hospitals" Guests: McCurdy, Layton.: Scott, Richard.: Sellers, Edward.: Wilson, Larry.: Seward, John.: Wiles, Paul., 15 September 1994 (Item Program Number S1024, 2414)
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1288
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7222
  - "Mini-Series on Crime: Part I: Does Punishment Deter Crime?" Guests: Du Pont, Pierre S. [Du Pont, Pete; DuPont, Pete]: Goodman, John C.: Hightower, Jim.: Sanders, Harold Barefoot, Jr.: Bronstein, Alvin., 4 October 1994 (Item Program Number S1025, 2415)
    Background File: Box/Folder 98: 12
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 138: 3
    Transcript: Box/Folder 186: 13
    Program details: On one thing host and guests are all agreed: our current criminal-justice system is broke and needs fixing. But what is cause and what is effect? Is there even such a thing as deterrence? Mr. Bronstein doesn't think so: "We have the most punitive, incarcerative country in the world, ten times as much as most Western European countries, and our crime keeps going up." Mr. Goodman points out a racial discrepancy: "The homicide rate among Caucasians in the United States is lower than it is in England, and on a par with most European countries. What's taking the United States off the map in these international comparisons is the very high crime rate in our minority communities, mainly in inner cities, where the victims as well as the perpetrators are often black." Mr. Hightower seems to agree, although with a twist: "Most auto theft is not about getting a car. Most auto theft is about carjacking, is about crack cocaine, is about none of the rationality that six white guys sitting around this table here know anything about." So why should we keep trying? Because, as Judge Sanders puts it, "I don't know of anyone in this room here who feels safe." A last word from Mr. Bronstein: "If Mr. Buckley ran his sailboat the way we fight crime in this country, he'd be fish food today."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1289
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7223
  - "Mini-Series on Crime: Part II: Is the Solution to Crime More Punishment?" Guests: Du Pont, Pierre S. [Du Pont, Pete; DuPont, Pete]: Goodman, John C.: Hightower, Jim.: Sanders, Harold Barefoot, Jr.: Bronstein, Alvin., 4 October 1994 (Item Program Number S1026, 2416)
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1290
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7224
  - "Mini-Series on Crime: Part III: Do We Need Prisons at All?" Guests: Du Pont, Pierre S.[Du Pont, Pete; DuPont, Pete]: Goodman, John C.: Colson, Charles W.: Bright, Stephen B., 1948-: Harris, Jean., 4 October 1994 (Item Program Number S1027, 2417)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 138: 4
    Transcript: Box/Folder 186: 14
    Program details: The tone changes in this installment, with the addition of two guests who know prisons from the inside. Mr. Colson, in particular, has thought long and hard about what we might do differently: "You can punish someone very severely, white collar or blue collar, without necessarily putting him in prison. I was in a prison dormitory with twenty guys ... who had done car theft and petty stock swindling--$3,000, this kind of scam. If you put those people cleaning out bedpans in the hospital or doing some public work for three or four years and take away their weekends, that's severe punishment. You don't have to lock them up at a cost of $30,000 a year to the taxpayers." ... Mrs. Harris: "One thing I think you've overlooked completely is that when we're making restitution to victims a very large percentage of people in prison were victims before they got to prison. I don't know what the percentage is, but I know it's over 10 per cent of the women at Bedford [the prison Mrs. Harris was in] who were raped as little children, who have had all sorts of terrible things--they come in with ulcerated sores where they've been stabbed with rusty knives."
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1291
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7225
  - "Mini-Series on Crime: Part IV: Realistic Insights into Crime and Punishment" Guests: Du Pont, Pierre S.: Goodman, John C.: Colson, Charles W.: Bright, Stephen B., 1948-: Harris, Jean., 4 October 1994 (Item Program Number S1028, 2418)
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1292
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7226
  - "The Bell Curve of Intelligence" Guests: Murray, Charles A.: Holt, Jim.: Botstein, Leon., 29 November 1994 (Item Program Number S1029, 2419)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 138: 5
    Transcript: Box/Folder 186: 15
    Program details: Richard Herrnstein (who had died of cancer just before The Bell Curve was published) and Charles Murray had expected their book to stir up controversy; they hadn't been quite prepared for the sheer dishonesty of much of the criticism. That does not apply to today's guests: for starters, although Messrs. Holt and Botstein are both highly critical of the book, they have both clearly read it. One sample: LB: "I came away with a sense that you have no real optimism whatsoever that there is anything that society collectively can do to improve radically the performance of the people at the bottom of the bell-shaped curve." CM: "I won't argue with that." This discussion, like the book itself, has serious implications for our education system, urban society, and indeed the shape of American democracy.
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1293
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7227
  - "The IQ Controversy: What's Going On?" Guests: Murray, Charles A.: Holt, Jim.: Botstein, Leon., 29 November 1994 (Item Program Number S1030, 2420)
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1294
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7228
  - "The Women's Movement: Part I" Guests: Fox-Genovese, Elizabeth, 1941-: Huffington, Arianna Stassinopoulos, 1950-: Alvare, Helen.: Friedan, Betty.: Burstein, Karen S.: Paglia, Camille, 1947-: Kolbert, Kathryn., 7 December 1994 (Item Program Number S1031, 2421)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 138: 8
    Transcript: Box/Folder 186: 16
    Program details: Typically, the free-form discussion following a Firing Line debate is fairly rambunctious. This one is gloriously off the charts. When the shouting subsides enough for sentences to be heard, they are well worth listening to. EFG: "The original women's movement has succeeded brilliantly. It is frequently said that the 1980s were a backlash against women, yet during the 1980s women went from earning 63 cents on the male dollar to earning 95 or more cents on the male dollar for entry-level positions. No social group in history has revolutionized their status in comparable fashion." ... ASH: "Please wake up, Betty! Something very fundamental is happening and you don't have a clue. There is a fundamental revolution happening that is about people recognizing that in the last thirty years we have spent $5 trillion on welfare and every single indicator is worse than it was." ... KK: "The original question of this show is: Has the women's movement gone too far? And I think the answer is, We haven't gone far enough. There is real injustice continuing to exist in this nation as a result of gender discrimination."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1297
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7231
  - "The Women's Movement: Part II" Guests: Fox-Genovese, Elizabeth, 1941-: Huffington, Arianna Stassinopoulos, 1950-: Alvare, Helen.: Friedan, Betty.: Burstein, Karen S.: Paglia, Camille, 1947-: Kolbert, Kathryn., 7 December 1994 (Item Program Number S1032, 2422)
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1298
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7232
  - "What Now for Russia?" Guests: Remnick, David., 29 November 1994 (Item Program Number S1033, 2423)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 138: 9
    Transcript: Box/Folder 186: 17
    Program details: A gloomy but informative discussion of the shape post-Soviet society has taken and may be expected to take in the future. DR: "My feeling about Reagan is that he played an incredible, somewhat instinctual role, a somewhat political and very hard-headed role in the collapse of the Soviet Union." ... "There is a lot of disenchantment among the people who were in the forefront in the late Eighties or early Nineties. People who ... saw Dostoyevsky scholars liberating Russia from its enslavement, all of a sudden found themselves poor and ignored and irrelevant.... What was needed in society were not saints, scholars, and truth-tellers, but accountants, traders, whatever is needed to build a capitalist nation."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1295
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7229
  - "Higher Interest Rates: Good or Bad? Part I" Guests: Levy, David A.: Kemp, Jack.: Martin, Preston.: Rubenstein, Edwin S.: Kuttner, Robert., 11 January 1995 (Item Program Number S1034, 2424)
    Background File: Box/Folder 98: 13
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 138: 10
    Program details: WFB warns us at the outset: "The ambitious purpose of this and the succeeding hour is to ponder the Federal Reserve Board's apparent attitude towards interest rates, and also to introduce the uninitiated--which includes your moderator--to the arcana of interest-rate practices and to the rather special vocabulary used in discussing the question. Keep your eyes on me. As long as I continue to sit here, you can stick around. If you see me slide away, you are at liberty to turn to another channel." In fact, although the discussion of interest rates, inflation, taxes, and more is often highly technical, Mr. Buckley sticks around, and so should we. One sample from Mr. Martin: "People in Washington do not know what is going on in the real world.... The mistake the central bank makes as it evolves is making governors out of staff people who have worked at the Fed for 39 years and 4 months and never really listened to the bank presidents of the 12 Fed banks when they tell you what's going on in New York and New Jersey and how sick that submarket really is."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1299
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7233
  - "Higher Interest Rates: Good or Bad? Part II" Guests: Levy, David A.: Kemp, Jack.: Martin, Preston.: Rubenstein, Edwin S.: Kuttner, Robert., 11 January 1995 (Item Program Number S1035, 2425)
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1300
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7234
  - "How Tax Cuts Look for '95: Part I" Guests: Levy, David A.: Kemp, Jack.: Regan, Edward V.: Kuttner, Robert., 11 January 1995 (Item Program Number S1036, 2426)
    Background File: Box/Folder 98: 14
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 138: 11
    Transcript: Box/Folder 186: 18
    Program details: The Republicans, led by Newt Gingrich, had just taken control of the House of Representatives for the first time in forty years, and tax cuts were a big part of their "Contract with America." But they were far from the only tax-cutters: President Clinton, House Majority Leader turned Minority Leader Richard Gephardt, Senator Phil Gramm--all God's chillun had tax-cut plans. This show, no less technical than its predecessor, brilliantly clarifies the points at issue: across-the-board versus targeted cuts; the capital-gains tax; spending and the Balanced Budget Amendment. RK: "As that well-known Bolshevik Herb Stein, Nixon's former chief economist, wrote in this week's New Republic, you could have a deficit of 2.5 per cent of the gross domestic product forever, and as along as the economy was growing faster than the deficit, it wouldn't be a problem. So I think this balanced-budget mania is absolutely counterproductive."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1301
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7235
  - "How Tax Cuts Look for '95: Part II" Guests: Levy, David A.: Kemp, Jack.: Regan, Edward V.: Kuttner, Robert., 11 January 1995 (Item Program Number S1037, 2427)
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1302
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7236
  - "Is New York City Governable?" Guests: Giuliani, Rudolph W., 23 January 1995 (Item Program Number S1038, 2428)
    Background File: Box/Folder 99: 1
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 138: 12
    Transcript: Box/Folder 186: 19
    Program details: His Honor answers the title question with a resounding "Yes!" He backs up his enthusiasm with persuasive details, on matters ranging from pornography to illegal immigration to taxes to homelessness, and argues his case for engaging the not-for-profit private sector instead of having the city government try to do everything itself. One sample: RG: "Had I been elected five years ago [without the intervening administration of David Dinkins, who defeated Mayor Koch], I could not have done the things that I was able to do four years later. Unfortunately the shattering of the private sector and some of the heavy increases in crime made possible the things that we were able to do."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1303
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/7237